[0] That, Virtue, as had been observed by the poets (in many passages which he well knew the jury would have, word for word, at the tips of their tongues;
[1] whereat the juryÆs countenances displayed a guilty consciousness that they knew nothing about the passages), was in a manner contagious;
[2] more especially the bright virtue known as patriotism, or love of country.
[3] That, the lofty example of this immaculate and unimpeachable witness for the Crown, to refer to whom however unworthily was an honour, had communicated itself to the prisonerÆs servant, and had engendered in him a holy determination to examine his masterÆs table-drawers and pockets, and secrete his papers.
[4] That, he (Mr. Attorney-General) was prepared to hear some disparagement attempted of this admirable servant;
[5] but that, in a general way, he preferred him to his (Mr. Attorney-GeneralÆs) brothers and sisters, and honoured him more than his (Mr.
[6] Attorney-GeneralÆs) father and mother.
[7] That, he called with confidence on the jury to come and do likewise.
[8] That, the evidence of these two witnesses, coupled with the documents of their discovering that would be produced, would show the prisoner to have been furnished with lists of his MajestyÆs forces, and of their disposition and preparation, both by sea and land, and would leave no doubt that he had habitually conveyed such information to a hostile power.
[9] That, these lists could not be proved to be in the prisonerÆs handwriting;
[10] but that it was all the same;
[11] that, indeed, it was rather the better for the prosecution, as showing the prisoner to be artful in his precautions.
[12] That, the proof would go back five years, and would show the prisoner already engaged in these pernicious missions, within a few weeks before the date of the very first action fought between the British troops and the Americans.
[13] That, for these reasons, the jury, being a loyal jury (as he knew they were), and being a responsible jury (as _they_ knew they were), must positively find the prisoner Guilty, and make an end of him, whether they liked it or not.
[14] That, they never could lay their heads upon their pillows;
[15] that, they never could tolerate the idea of their wives laying their heads upon their pillows;
[16] that, they never could endure the notion of their children laying their heads upon their pillows;
[17] in short, that there never more could be, for them or theirs, any laying of heads upon pillows at all, unless the prisonerÆs head was taken off.
[18] That head Mr. Attorney-General concluded by demanding of them, in the name of everything he could think of with a round turn in it, and on the faith of his solemn asseveration that he already considered the prisoner as good as dead and gone.
[19] When the Attorney-General ceased, a buzz arose in the court as if a cloud of great blue-flies were swarming about the prisoner, in anticipation of what he was soon to become.
[20] When toned down again, the unimpeachable patriot appeared in the witness-box.
[21] Mr. Solicitor-General then, following his leaderÆs lead, examined the patriot:
[22] John Barsad, gentleman, by name.
[23] The story of his pure soul was exactly what Mr. Attorney-General had described it to be--perhaps, if it had a fault, a little too exactly.
[24] Having released his noble bosom of its burden, he would have modestly withdrawn himself, but that the wigged gentleman with the papers before him, sitting not far from Mr. Lorry, begged to ask him a few questions.
[25] The wigged gentleman sitting opposite, still looking at the ceiling of the court.
[26] Had he ever been a spy himself?
[27] No, he scorned the base insinuation.
[28] What did he live upon?
[29] His property.
[30] Where was his property?
[31] He didnÆt precisely remember where it was.
[32] What was it?
[33] No business of anybodyÆs.
[34] Had he inherited it?
[35] Yes, he had.
[36] From whom?
[37] Distant relation.
[38] Very distant?
[39] Rather.
[40] Ever been in prison?
[41] Certainly not.
[42] Never in a debtorsÆ prison?
[43] DidnÆt see what that had to do with it.
[44] Never in a debtorsÆ prison?--Come, once again.
[45] Never?
[46] Yes.
[47] How many times?
[48] Two or three times.
[49] Not five or six?
[50] Perhaps.
[51] Of what profession?
[52] Gentleman.
[53] Ever been kicked?
[54] Might have been.
[55] Frequently?
[56] No.
[57] Ever kicked downstairs?
[58] Decidedly not;
[59] once received a kick on the top of a staircase, and fell downstairs of his own accord.
[60] Kicked on that occasion for cheating at dice?
[61] Something to that effect was said by the intoxicated liar who committed the assault, but it was not true.
[62] Swear it was not true?
[63] Positively.
[64] Ever live by cheating at play?
[65] Never.
[66] Ever live by play?
[67] Not more than other gentlemen do.
[68] Ever borrow money of the prisoner?
[69] Yes.
[70] Ever pay him?
[71] No.
[72] Was not this intimacy with the prisoner, in reality a very slight one, forced upon the prisoner in coaches, inns, and packets?
[73] No.
[74] Sure he saw the prisoner with these lists?
[75] Certain.
[76] Knew no more about the lists?
[77] No.
[78] Had not procured them himself, for instance?
[79] No.
[80] Expect to get anything by this evidence?
[81] No.
[82] Not in regular government pay and employment, to lay traps?
[83] Oh dear no.
[84] Or to do anything?
[85] Oh dear no.
[86] Swear that?
